touch briefly on looking at how current
there is a cognitive development from
the skills based models codify the
higher levels for the developmental
processes of cognitive development I'll
just briefly mention Michael Commons
he's responsible for the notion of the
higher levels of formal operation go
from systemic thinking to meta systemic
thinking to paradigm our paradigmatic
thinking to what he calls cross
paradigmatic thinking and so by
measuring the problem-solving
methodologies of people the level of
cognitive capacity can be codified in
these different ways so the
sophistication it measures a
sophistication of reasoning with
abstractions now the interesting thing
to note is that in the skills based
models they follow PA JS philosophy
pretty tightly then p IJ understood
development as um eliminating
addictions so if you're working on a
problem if you're working on a problem
to seek understanding then at a certain
level of a problem you have a
contradiction between the empirical
facts or what you observe you see and
your ability to explain it so you can
come up with a logical contradiction but
the contradiction is between your
ability to explain in the world so the
contradiction is between the expand and
and the observation so this is a very
scientific mind set these they do not
really talked about in the skill sets
models they don't really look at the
inherent paradoxes or contradictions of
the mind itself it's basically a
scientific methodology an empirical kind
of approach to cognitive skills
development and so that's what you see
what Commons is doing is that if you
observing phenomenon and you have a
linear pre systematically of a linear
type of understanding then eventually
the problems are going to be more
complex and you're going to have a
contradiction between your prediction
let's say and the outcome based upon
your theory and so this this actually
fouls quite closely to someone like Hyun
so the contradiction is not inside the
mind but it's between the empirical
observations experimental setup the
ability to predict and so from going
when a linear understanding no longer
functions then a systematic approach
does better and then when a systematic
understanding no longer is effective
then the developmental trajectory is
toward being medicine somatic and when a
meta systematic or so meta systematic
looks at systems so for a meta
systematic the object of inquiry is the
system itself once the meta systemic
level no longer produces effects then
there needs to be a paradigm change so
that the the the foundational
assumptions that have been there all
along tend to get changed in a paradigm
shift then there are systems of
paradigms ways to look at problems and
systems of paradigms which are cross
paradigmatic types of reasoning so
Michael Commons is a model and there was
very bird during many different versions
of it are based upon looking at problem
solving cognitive capacity within this
framework there's not a lot of
dialectical indication or exploration in
his system and not in the skills based
developmental camp at all in general
one of the most interesting models of
development in the skills camp is that
of Harvard philosopher psychologists
current Fisher and he has a skills or
task-based developmental theory that
looks at development in the progress of
development in a very interesting way
and it's been very successful in many
ways and so he categorizes levels of
engagement has primary levels of skills
and task task about actions the next
level is representations the next level
would be that he calls abstractions and
the next level up he calls principles
now the interesting thing is that the
movement between each one of these
levels Fischer has identified as being a
pattern so there's a similar pattern and
it's this pattern that he is very
interested in identifying and studying
and so the pattern goes from what he
calls single things to mappings to
systems so what he's saying is that
unlike comments is that there's
Systems type movements or developments
in the lower ranges of cognitive
capacity it's just that we don't they're
so simple the systems are so simple that
we haven't looked at them as simple
systems and so for example a toddler app
actually goes from performing single
actions to mapping those actions mapping
of actions cognitively in several
different way so you have a couple
different mapping relationships and then
he takes those mapping of actions and
organizes them into a simple system so
there's some kind of organization of the
actions the referee the mapping of those
actions cognitively and into a simple
system and at a certain point this
system itself becomes so manipulative or
the person that the simp this this
system this system of maps of actions
can become its own single thing it
becomes a single representation and then
the still a young person here tends to
have a collection of single
representations that get mapped as
napped representations and as at the
point they get enough collections of
math representations the certain stage
the individual creates a system of these
mapped representations and that after a
certain pair
period of time and cognitive growth
capacity which is is pushed or pulled by
the need to develop skills through
various tasks or problems that the
individual confronts then eventually the
person is able to look at these systems
or representations as single things and
in this case they become single
abstractions and then the single
abstractions not surprisingly get mapped
abstractions and you get a collections
of these mapped abstractions that the
individual can utilize for problem
solving but eventually all these this
collection of mapped abstractions right
become themselves a system and so the
individual systematize is the collection
of mapped abstractions and the
abstractions were mapped from
abstractions that were once systems or
representations and the systems or
representations or mapped from single
representations that were once you only
available to the individual as systems
events of actions and so you have this
movement back in up levels through this
process of taking what's available
initially only as a single item mapping
it cognitively at which point it's but
it eventually becomes able to be
integrated or organized into system
eventually that system of organization
can be handled again as a single thing
in the next higher level in the last
move in Fishers scheme
is that these map the systems of mapped
abstractions then become principles and
they become single principles and the
assumption is that then that can go on
from there so this is very interesting
and what's one of the things that
interested me about this system and one
of Curt Fisher's students is zach's
dying and I asked him if in their
studies did anyone ever experienced a
principle so when they're doing studies
and they find out that they belissa
tadesse movement forward principles does
anyone ever experienced principles not
as being up this sequence but somehow
being foundational to the actions in the
first place right so did anyone ever
find a principle that they felt was
actually there all along experience that
principle as foundational even to the
actions so along this whole sequence was
there ever this undertow right this
question of an undertow and zach stein
said that to his knowledge that had
never been articulated and for me that
would be key that would be key if a
person experienced this progression up
to a principle as actually seeing that
the principal might be foundational to
the process so ontological ii prior now
this does not exist in Kurt Fisher's
system but because we're not really
going to come back to curtain Fisher
system just wanted to to share with you
that if this would be for me the
oh that would signal a post post formal
beyond a formal operational
understanding and so the flavor of this
will say and self has been developed in
some of the other developmental model
based on meaning and it has to do with
the fact that the inquiry turns inward
toward the assumptions or they toured
the processes in the mind itself but
this does not happen or is not part of
what's measured in the skills task
development models okay now